Yaseswini Neelamraju, PhD

yaseswini.1404@gmail.com

Bioinformatics scientist with 10 years of professional experience in analyzing next-generation DNA and RNA sequencing data primarily from human subjects diagnosed with cancer. I am committed to developing and applying computational tools to new and/or existing genomic data and contributing to translational research.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Jan2024 - Present Research Scientist, Bioinformatics & Computational Biology

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

Jun-Aug,2022 Summer Intern in Predictive Sciences

Bristol-Myers Squibb, Cambridge, MA

- Reproduced and applied an existing tumor microenvironment (TME) subtype method to pancreatic cancer data from TCGA
- Modified the existing TME subtype classification approach for pan-cancer data
- Developed an R shiny application implementing existing and improved TME classification method on tumor data

2017 – 2018 Bioinformatics Analyst

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA

- Identified DNA methylation and transcriptional changes in patients diagnosed and relapsed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML)
- Contributed to three peer-reviewed manuscripts through collaborative research.

2015 – 2017 Bioinformatics Analyst

Weill Cornell Medicine, New York, USA

- Identified DNA methylation and transcriptional changes in patients diagnosed and relapsed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML)
- Identified DNA methylation changes contributing to age-related changes in *TET2* knock down zebrafish developing myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)

2013 – 2015 Bioinformatician

Indiana University-Purdue University, Indiana, USA

- Analyzed and identified mutational landscape of RNA binding proteins across 6000 cancer genomics constituting 26 cancer types from TCGA consortium
- Identified splicing alternations contributing to endocrine resistance in breast cancer cell lines in collaborative research with IU School of Medicine.
- Curated RNA binding proteins and their known functional characteristics identified in humans to construct a database useful for researchers in the field

EDUCATION

2018 – 2023 Doctor of Philosophy

Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics

University of Virginia, Charlottesville

Major: Bioinformatics

Thesis: Identifying molecular signatures associated with aging in myeloid malignancies

2011 – 2013 Master's in Technology, Bioinformatics

Department of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics

University of Hyderabad, India

Thesis: Integrating disease-gene and protein-protein interactions to identify candidate genes for Psoriasis using network theory.

2007 – 2011 Bachelor of Technology, Biotechnology

Department of Biotechnology

Sreenidhi Institute of Science and Technology, Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, India

MENTORSHIP

2022 -- Present University of Virginia

Co-mentor for BME capstone undergraduate students in developing prognostic models based on DNA methylation and gene expression data generated from patients diagnosed with AML

TEACHING ASSISTANTSHIP

2021 – 2022 University of Virginia

Mentored an undergraduate student in learning the basics of computational biology.

- Basic programming in R
- Survival analysis

Spring, 2017 University of Virginia

Teaching assistant for workshops on

- Introduction to R
- Advanced data manipulation in R
- Visualization in R using ggplot2

2014 Indiana University Purdue University

Analysis of microarray array using R

SKILLS

- Experience working with human clinical trial data
- Experience working on high-performance computing systems
- I have experience working with large genetic, genomic, and clinical datasets identified from TCGA, DepMap, Beat-AML, ENCODE, NCBI GEO, cBioPortal
- Experience in integrative analysis using multiple genomic datasets and clinical information
- Excellent oral and written communicable skills
- Excellent molecular biology background.

Sequence analysis	Sequence alignment tools (DNA and protein): BLAST, BLAT, ClustalW
NGS data	DNA methylation (Bisulphite sequencing) Bulk & single-cell RNA sequencing ChIP-sequencing ATAC-sequencing
Data analysis tools	Microarray data analysis Genome Visualization – UCSC genome browser, IGV

	Methylkit, MethylSig, MACS, Differential peak analysis using DESeq2 FastQC, STAR, HISAT, Salmon, Kallisto, TopHat, Bowtie, Differential gene expression analysis (DESeq2), Gene co-expression networks (WGCNA), Deconvolution analysis methods for bulkRNAseq – CIBERSORT, Single-cell RNAsequencing, Splicing analysis using rMATS
Functional genomics	Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA), single sample Gene set enrichment analysis (ssGSEA), Gene set variation analysis (GSVA), Ingenuity Pathway analysis (IPA), EnrichR, GProfileR, GREAT (Genomic Regions Enrichment of Annotations Tool), Transcription factor binding analysis (HOMER, MEME suite of tools).
Systems biology	Network analysis
Biostatistics	Application of statistical tests to genomic data, Survival analysis, Cox proportional hazards model, Correlation
Machine Learning	Principal Component analysis, K-means clustering, Hierarchical clustering, Linear models, Logistic regression, Generalized linear regression methods, principal component regression (PCR), partial least squares regression (PLS), Xtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost)
Operating Systems	Linux, Mac OS and Windows
Scripting/Programming Languages	C (beginner), Perl, R, Python
Version Control	GitHub, R markdown
Workflow Management	Nextflow
Web development	HTML, CSS

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. <u>Neelamraju Y</u>.*, E. Gjini, S. Chhangawala, H. Fan, S. He, C. B. Jing, A. T. Nguyen, S. Prajapati, C. Sheridan, Y. Houvras, A. Melnick, A. T. Look and F. E. Garrett-Bakelman (2023). "Depletion of tet2 results in age-dependent changes in DNA methylation and gene expression in a zebrafish model of myelodysplastic syndrome." Front Hematol 2.
- Rapaport, F.*, K. Seier*, Y. Neelamraju*, D. Hassane, T. Baslan, D. T. Gildea, S. Haddox, T. Lee, H. M. Murdock, C. Sheridan, A. Thurmond, L. Wang, M. Carroll, L. D. Cripe, H. Fernandez, C. E. Mason, E. Paietta, G. J. Roboz, Z. Sun, M. S. Tallman, Y. Zhang, M. Gonen, R. Levine, A. M. Melnick, M. Kleppe and F. E. Garrett-Bakelman (2022). "Integrative analysis identifies an older female-linked AML patient group with better risk in ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group's clinical trial E3999." Blood Cancer J 12(9): 137.
- 3. Barreyro, L., A. M. Sampson, C. Ishikawa, K. M. Hueneman, K. Choi, M. A. Pujato, S. Chutipongtanate, et al. "Blocking Ube2n Abrogates Oncogenic Immune Signaling in Acute Myeloid Leukemia." Sci Transl Med 14, no. 635 (Mar 9 2022): eabb7695.
- 4. Rapaport F, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Baslan T, Hassane D, Gruszczynska A, Robert de Massy M, et al. Genomic and evolutionary portraits of disease relapse in acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia. 2021.
- 5. Olson TL, Cheon H, Xing JC, Olson KC, Paila U, Hamele CE, et al. Frequent somatic TET2 mutations in chronic NK-LGL leukemia with distinct patterns of cytopenias. Blood. 2021;138(8):662-73.
- 6. Abshiru NA, Sikora JW, Camarillo JM, Morris JA, Compton PD, Lee T, et al. Targeted detection and quantitation of histone modifications from 1,000 cells. PLoS One. 2020;15(10):e0240829.

^{*} Authors contributed equally

- 7. Gokmen-Polar Y, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Goswami CP, Gu Y, Gu X, Nallamothu G, et al. Splicing factor ESRP1 controls ER-positive breast cancer by altering metabolic pathways. EMBO Rep. 2019;20(2).
- 8. <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Gonzalez-Perez A, Bhat-Nakshatri P, Nakshatri H, Janga SC. Mutational landscape of RNA-binding proteins in human cancers. RNA Biol. 2018;15(1):115-29.
- 9. Nishtala S, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC. Dissecting the expression relationships between RNA-binding proteins and their cognate targets in eukaryotic post-transcriptional regulatory networks. Sci Rep. 2016; 6:25711.
- 10. <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Hashemikhabir S, Janga SC. The human RBPome: from genes and proteins to human disease. J Proteomics. 2015;127(Pt A):61-70.
- 11. Hashemikhabir S, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC. Database of RNA binding protein expression and disease dynamics (READ DB). Database (Oxford). 2015;2015: bav072.
- 12. Gokmen-Polar Y, Vladislav IT, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC, Badve S. Prognostic impact of HOTAIR expression is restricted to ER-negative breast cancers. Sci Rep. 2015; 5:8765.
- 13. Gokmen-Polar Y, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Goswami CP, Gu X, Nallamothu G, Janga SC, et al. Expression levels of SF3B3 correlate with prognosis and endocrine resistance in estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer. Mod Pathol. 2015;28(5):677-85.
- 14. Chaturvedi P, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Arif W, Kalsotra A, Janga SC. Uncovering RNA binding proteins associated with age and gender during liver maturation. Sci Rep. 2015; 5:9512.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

POSTER

2023 65th ASH Annual Meeting and Exposition

"A pro-inflammatory gene signature characterizes a better risk aged AML patient group in ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group's clinical trial E3999"

FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference, FASEB, August 2023

"A pro-inflammatory gene signature characterizes a better risk aged AML patient group in ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group's clinical trial E3999" – also selected for lightning talk

FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference, FASEB, July 2021 (Virtual conference) "An integrative analysis identifies a female-linked group that associates with better risk for AML patients older than sixty years of age in a clinical trial of the ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group (E3999)"

2015 Cold Spring Harbor Meeting. Systems Biology: Global regulation of Gene Expression "Mutational landscape of RNA Binding Proteins in human cancer"

2014 Rustbelt RNA Meeting, 2014, Pittsburg, PA

"The human RBPome: from genes and proteins to human disease" – poster presentation

ORAL

2017 lst Annual Commonwealth of Virginia Cancer Research Conference 2017, Charlottesville "AMLs with high methylation in GADD45A promoter exhibit distinct molecular profiles associated with poor outcome"

HACKATHONS

2023 Bio Hackathon organized by St Jude's Children's Research Hospital

• Developed shiny modules to visualize DNA methylation data

CONFERENCES & WORKSHOP ATTENDANCE

2020	Biomedical Data Science (Virtual conference) – CSHL
2016	Epi workshop jointly organized by Weill Cornell Medicine, Hospital for Special Surgery and
	New York City College of Technology
2015	Advances in Genome Science, NYC Illumina User Group Meeting 2015.
2015	Great Lakes Bioinformatics Conference

HONORS, AWARDS, AND SCHOLARSHIP

2023	UVA's Cancer Center trainee travel award to attend the hematologic malignancies conference organized by FASEB
2015	Stipend award to attend the Cold Spring Laboratory Meeting on "Systems Biology: Global regulation of Gene Expression" held in Puerto Rico from 28th Jan, 15 - 01st Feb, 15)
2011	SNIST-ISTE Gold medal for securing first rank amongst the students of B.Tech Biotechnology Class of 2011.
2007-2010	Academic excellence awards while pursuing Bachelor in Biotechnology for the years 2007 - 2010.

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

2024 - Present	Member, website development team for the Women-in-bioinformatics (Boston chapter)
2022	Participated in the Skill2Give event organized by Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMS)
2021 - 2023	Co-organizer of CPHG (Center for Public Health Genomics) computing club.
2022	BMG recruitment, UVA student host for 1 weekend
2019 - 2020	BMG recruitment, UVA, student host for 1-2 weekends per year
2019-2020	Volunteer Coordinator at Society for the Promotion of Indian Classical Music and Culture
	Amongst Youth (SPICMACAY), UVA Chapter
2019	Participated in the data hackathon organized by the UVA Biomedical Data Sciences
	Training Program
2017-2018	Volunteer at Society for the Promotion of Indian Classical Music and Culture Amongst
	Youth (SPICMACAY), UVA Chapter

WEBSITES

LinkedIn: Yaseswini Neelamraju | LinkedIn

Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=wzrrprAAAAAJ

GitHub: https://github.com/Yaseswini